Guide to the Carl Geiser Audio Collection ALBA.AUDIO.004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Carl Geiser Audio Collection
1977-1986
ALBA.AUDIO.004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
2.0 linear feet (35 audiocassettes)
Carl Frederick Geiser was born in Orrville, Ohio on December 10, 1910. He fought with the International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War as a member of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and was taken prisoner and held in a fascist prisoner of war camp for a year before being released in April 1939. After a successful career as an aeronautical engineer, he retired in 1971 and began to research and write a history of American volunteers captured during the Spanish Civil War. His labors resulted in the publication of Prisoners of the Good Fight: The Spanish Civil War 1936-1939 in 1986. This collection consists of 35 audiocassettes, most of them interviews with former prisoners conducted as part of the research for Geiser's book. Also included are some taped "reflections" by Geiser in trips to Cuba and Spain.
Geiser, Carl
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carl Geiser Papers (ALBA 004) ALBA Vertical Files: Individuals (ALBA VF 2) Robert Steck Audio Collection (ALBA AUDIO 104) Robert Steck Papers (ALBA 104) Randall Smith: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Historical Commission Records (ALBA 003)
Scope and Content Note
Most of the 35 tapes in this collection contain interviews, comments and discussions recorded in the 1970s and 80s in connection with research for Carl Geiser's book, Prisoners of the Good Fight. Also included are Geiser's taped "reflections' on the Spanish Civil War and on a trip to Cuba.
Historical/Biographical Note
Carl Frederick Geiser was born in Orrville, Ohio on December 10, 1910. He was the oldest of six children; his father, a farmer, died in the influenza epidemic at the end of World War I, and his mother a year later of tuberculosis. His maternal grandparents, Swiss immigrants who spoke little English, raised Geiser and his siblings. The young Geiser received his primary education in a one-room schoolhouse while helping to tend the family's sixteen-acre farm. Upon his graduation from Orrville High School in 1928, he enrolled in the YMCA School of Technology (later Fenn College) in Cleveland, where he majored in electrical engineering.
In 1932, following the establishment of diplomatic relations between the United States and the Soviet Union, Geiser was part of the first National Student Federation mission to travel to the newly recognized country. Impressed by the Soviet system and the tenets of socialist ideology, Geiser joined the Young Communist League on his return to Ohio. He was active in the American Student Union in Cleveland and served as a delegate to the First Student Congress Against War and Fascism held in Chicago. It was there that Geiser met his future wife Sylvia, a teacher and organizer who shared his political fervor. The couple moved to New York where they were absorbed into a dynamic culture of political activism and organizing. Geiser wrote press releases and edited International Labor Defense bulletins, organized for the League against War and Fascism, and in 1936 was elected to the National Committee of the Young Communist League.
On April 13, 1937 Geiser boarded the S.S. Georgic to join the International Brigades massing in defense of the Spanish Republic. He served as an ammunition carrier at the Battle of Brunete, saw action at Quinto, and advanced to the rank of Lieutenant and then Political Commissar. Wounded at the conflict at Fuentes de Ebro, Geiser was hospitalized for three months. Returned to the front as Commissar of the Mackenzie-Papineau Battalion in January 1938, he was captured by fascist forces on April 1, 1938. For the next year, he was interned at San Pedro de Cardeña, along with over 650 International Brigades prisoners. Through the efforts of the Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and the U.S. State Department, Geiser and a group of 71 Americans were released in April 1939.
Geiser returned to New York and secured an engineering position with Liquidometer, a manufacturer of aeronautic equipment. By the early 1970s, Geiser turned his attention once more to Spain. Upon retirement at age 71, Geiser began to write a comprehensive history of American volunteers captured during the Spanish Civil War. With the assistance of fellow prisoner Robert Steck, Geiser amassed biographical information on the 120 Americans incarcerated in Spanish prisons. He also corresponded with over 150 veterans worldwide to solicit their reminiscences, and traveled to archives in the United States and Europe to conduct research. Five years of research and writing culminated in the publication of Prisoners of the Good Fight (Lawrence Hill and Co., 1986).
Abraham Lincoln Brigade.; Geiser, Carl; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade.; Audiocassettes.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Personal narratives.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Prisoners and prisons.
- Alexander, William, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 001)
- Allen, Richard Sanders, Apr 13, 1981 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 002)
- Amatniek, Ernest, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 003)
- Clemente Garcia, Santos; Hans Streuli (translation of a German letter), undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 004)
- Eggar, Dougal, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 005)
- Ersler, Gabriel, Sep 19 - Sep 23, 1983 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 006)
- Gilbert, Tony, Sep 10, 1986 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 007)
- Hafner, Otto (tape 1 of 3), Jul 20, 1981 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 008)
- Hafner, Otto (tape 2 of 3), Jul 20, 1981 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 009)
- Hafner, Otto (tape 3 of 3), Jul 20, 1981 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 010)
- Heinzman, Georg; Karl Loesch, 1981 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 011)
- Herman, Joe Hy, May 3, 1978 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 012)
- Jones, Tom, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 013)
- Kowalski, Arthur, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 014)
- Levitas, Maurice; Tom Jones (tape 2 of 2; related to tape 004-013 or 004-028?)), undated (Box ALBA Shared Access Audio 1, Drawer 2, Cassette 004-015)
  Levitas, Ruth
- Loesch, Karl, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 016)
- Lopez, Jules Herman (Cintron); Hy Wallach; Joseph Lafayette Young, Jul 31, 1977 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 017, Box Shared ALBA Access Box 1)
  Wallach, Nancy
- Lopez, Jules Herman (Cintron); Hy Wallach; Joseph Lafayette Young (committee meeting), Sep 17, 1978 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 018, Box Shared ALBA Access Box 1)
- Moon, Jimmy, Aug 15 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 019)
- Moon, Jimmy, Sep 12 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 020)
- Nelson, Steve; Jules Paivio (Nelson's greetings to the Mac Paps), Oct 1977 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 021)
- Ornitz, Louis Noah (tape 1 of 2), Jan 7, 1982 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 022)
- Ornitz, Louis Noah (tape 2 of 2), Jan 7, 1982 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 023)
- Riffe, Carl Herman, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 024)
- Riffe, Carl Herman; Velmar Edward Hodge, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 025)
- Streit, Herman (side 1); first meeting with Anti. Wider. Kom [Antifascist Historical Committee], Berlin (side 2)(tape 1 of 2), undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 026)
- Streit, Herman (tape 2 of 2), undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 027)
- Tenor, Leon; Maurice Levitas, Aug 30 (Box ALBA Shared Access Audio 1, Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 028)
- West, Frank; Documents on Prisoners at San Pedro de Cardena, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 029)
- West, Frank, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 030)
- Young, Joseph Lafayette, Jul 31, 1977 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 031)
- Interview with an Italian Woman re: Italian POWS Held by Republican Army, undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 032)
- Geiser, Carl; Reflections on Trip to Cuba, 1982 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 033)
- Geiser, Carl; Reflections on Spain (tape 1 of 2), Jun 8 - Jun 10 (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 034)
- Geiser, Carl; Reflections on Spain (tape 2 of 2) [from Madrid], undated (Drawer 2, Cassette 004- 035)